Guide to the J. Kent Clark Papers, 1954-2003 Consult repository
Caltech Archives
J. Kent Clark Papers,
1954-2003
Caltech Archives
Clark, J. Kent, 1917-
Consult repository
2 linear feet
J. Kent Clark, 1917-pres. Professor of English, CIT 1947-86. The papers include manuscripts of dramatic and musical works (with audio casettes), biographical sketches, essays, a manuscript of Clark's biography of Thomas, Earl of Wharton, and some correspondence (esp. with Walter Garner).
General
Contact Information:
Archives
California Institute of Technology
1200 East California Blvd.
Mail Code 015A-74
Pasadena, CA 91125
Phone: (626) 395-2704
Fax: (626) 793-8756
Email: archives@caltech.edu
URL: http://archives.caltech.edu
General
Processed by:
Charlotte E. Erwin
Date Completed:
August 23, 1993
Date Updated:
Through March 2003
Encoded by:
Francisco J. Medina
Access
The collection is open for research. Researchers must apply in writing for access.
Acquisition Information
The papers of J. Kent Clark have been donated to the Caltech Archives over a large period of time. Much of the collection was donated in 1990.
Biography
J. Kent Clark came to Caltech in 1947 as an instructor in English. He was born in 1917 inUtah, and educated at Brigham Young University and at Stanford. At Caltech he was one ofa group of outstanding teachers of the humanities who began their tenure following WorldWar II, at the end of the Millikan era. His renown on campus grew with the creation of aseries of musicals on campus life and characters between 1954 and 1988, in collaborationwith Elliott Davis. The musicals were performed by the Caltech Stock Company. A number ofsongs from these shows have achieved notoriety of their own. Clark also wrote musicalsand plays for organizations other than Caltech. He is the author of a novel, TheKing's Agent, and biographies of Goodwin and Thomas Wharton (the Tom Whartonbiography is still in progress). Clark's life and career are described in the oralhistory done for the Caltech Archives in 1990. He became Emeritus in 1986.
Scope and Content
J. Kent Clark's papers were given to the Archives over a period of time. The first itemsto be received were the musicals, which in most cases were represented by text, musicalscores, and frequently by audio cassettes as well. Of the remaining papers, the bulk wasgiven in 1990. In preparing the materials for use, it was decided to bring all of themtogether in one place, in the collection now called the Papers of J. Kent Clark. Theexception is the audio cassettes, which reside mostly--there are some exceptions--in theArchives' audio collection. Cross references to these audio cassettes are given in theGuide to the Papers. However, researchers should consult the separate guide to the audiocassette collection for some items which are not referenced in the papers. Threephonorecords of Clark's songs and musicals are also separately catalogued.
Musicals; Songs; California Institute of Technology; Caltech. Division of Humanities
- J. Kent Clark Papers
  - Section I: Dramatic and Musical Works
    - Musicals
      - The Road to Stockholm (The Appalling Life of Dr. Pauling) See also: audio cassette collection; phonorecord collection, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - [This is Science] (Show for the AAAS Meeting, Pasadena City College), 1955 (Folder 2)
      - Who is this Guy DuBridge? See also: audio cassette collection; phonorecord collection, 1956 (Folder 3)
      - Take Your Medicine; rev. 1985 [includes audio cassette], 1957-58 (Folder 4)
      - The Importance of Being Earnest See also: audio cassette collection, 1959 (Folder 5)
      - Committees [2 copies], 1960 (Folder 6)
      - What Makes Beadle Run?, 1961 (Folder 7)
      - The Organization Women, 1962 (Folder 8)
      - Lee and Sympathy [includes audio cassette] See also: audio cassette collection, 1966 (Folder 9)
      - A Broader View (Show for Caltech Y), 1966 (Folder 10)
      - The Bacher File See also: audio cassette collection, 1970 (Folder 11)
      - Beautiful Beckman [2 copies] See also: audio cassette collection, 1975 (Folder 12)
      - A Broader View (rev.) and Troll's Progress (Playreaders' Party), 1987 (Folder 13)
      - Middlekauf Cantata, 1987 (Folder 14)
      - Caltech Revisited: or Déjá, Déjá Vu, 1988 (Folder 15)
      - Selections from Kent Clark Shows [audio cassette] (Folder 16)
    - Song Collections
      - "Let's Advance on Science" and other songs [includes audio cassette] See also: phonorecord collection (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Retirement songs: R. Sharp, H. Wayland, H. Brown (Folder 2)
      - "Ballad of Chappaquiddick" and "The Richter Scale" [phonodisc] (Folder 3)
    - Show, Huntington Library celebration
      - Paradise Re-Lost [for James Thorpe], 1983 (Folder 4)
  - Section II: Literary Works
    - Profiles [Biographical sketches]
      - [Note on Profiles] (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Coltrin, Bill, 1982 (Folder 6)
      - Eagleson, Harvey, 1967 (Folder 7)
      - Eaton, Paul, 1976 (Folder 8)
      - Hershey, Wes, memorial service, 1989 (Folder 9)
      - Kent, Henry C. [JKC's grandfather; in letter to Clarence Kent], 1987 (Folder 10)
      - Kent, Percy D. and Sara [JKC's uncle and aunt], 1978 (Folder 11)
      - Langston, Beach, 1979 (Folder 12)
      - Oliver, Bob, retirement; Oliver, Darlene, memorial speech, 1988; 1987 (Folder 13)
      - Searle, Don, 1982-83 (Folder 14)
    - Essays and Other Writings
      - [Note on Essays] (Folder 15)
      - [Jonathan] Swift and the Dutch, 1954 (Folder 16)
      - Eliot's Poetic Theory and Practice, 1956 (Folder 17)
      - Readings in Rationalism, 1959 (Folder 18)
      - The Art Program at Caltech, 1971 (Folder 19)
      - Diatribe [re Jenijoy LaBelle; in letter to Peter Fay], 1976 (Folder 20)
      - The Creative Arts and Twentieth Century Education, 1979 (Folder 21)
      - Article on secretaries, 1986 (Folder 22)
      - Letter to students [re abolishing Invocation at Commencement], 1985 (Folder 23)
      - Humanities Division Working Papers:
        - The Inglorious Revolution, 1979 (Folder 24)
        - Lilliburlero (Chap. 16 of Goodwin Wharton biography), 1979
        - The Colonel and the Queen (Chap. 19 of Goodwin Wharton biography), 1980
        - The Search for the First Earl of Wharton [2 copies], 1988 (Folder 25)
        - Young Tom Wharton, 1989
        - Marriage á la Mode, 1990
        - The Third Whig, 1991
        - The Plot of "The Plot" [Ch. 9 of Wharton biography, n.d.]
      - Defense of Robert Oliver's George Woods and the World Bank, 1993 (Folder 26)
  - Section III: Personal
    - Vita (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Reunion Program, Brigham Young University, 1989 (Folder 28)
    - See also: Oral History Collection
    - See also: Audio Tape Collection
  - Supplement, 1994
    - Exclusion [Ch. 10-12 of the Wharton biography] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Search for Goodwin Wharton, 1976 (Folder 2)
    - The Publication of Goodwin Wharton... and the Search for Thomas, Earl of Wharton, 1984 (Folder 3)
  - Supplement, 1995
    - Anne Wharton [Ch. 13 of the Wharton biography] (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Outrages [Ch. 14 of the Wharton biography] (Folder 5)
    - Seizures [Ch. 15 of the Wharton biography] (Folder 6)
  - Supplement, 1996
    - Transcript of speech by J. C. Clark for 100th Founder's Day celebration of Gnome Club, 9 March 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letter to Denise Smith, 17 Jan 1996 (Folder 8)
    - Correpondence with Walter Garner
      - 1976-1978 (Folder 9)
      - 1979-1981 (Folder 10)
      - 1982-1984 (Folder 11)
      - 1985-1986 (Folder 12)
      - 1987-1988 (Folder 13)
      - 1989-1990 (Folder 14)
      - 1991-1992 (Folder 15)
      - 1993-1996 (Folder 16)
    - Letter about Elliott Davis (to Walter and Irene Garner), 20 Nov 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Supplement, 1997
    - Horses and Bridles [Ch. 19 of Tom Wharton Biography], November 1997 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Supplement, 1998
    - Speech to the Class of 1958 [, 15 May 1998] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Supplement, 1999
    - Wharton, Thomas, Draft for Dictionary of National Biography (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Supplement, 2001
    - Foreward to Diary of Martin Tangora (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - New Vita (1999): See 2.27
  - Supplement, 2002
    - Talk to Class of 1952, May 16, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Short essays
      - George Epstein's poetry (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Elegy on my brother: Ernest Eugene Clark (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Supplement, 2003
    - Huntington Library (with Carol B. Pearson), March 12, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- J. Kent Clark Audio Material
  - I. Audio Cassettes in Audio Cassette Archive
    - The Road to Stockholm [2 copies], 12-9-54
    - Who is This Guy DuBridge?, 12-7-56
    - [The Importance of Being Earnest], 10-22-59
    - What Makes Beadle Run?, 3-21-61
    - Caltech in E-flat, 4-28-66
    - Lee and Sympathy, 11-18-66
    - A Broader View [Caltech Y Anniversary], 1966
    - DuBridge Farewell Program, 1-12-69
    - DuBridge Farewell Dinner (also exists on reel-to-reel tape)
    - The Bacher File, 11-19-70
    - The Bacher Dinner
    - Beautiful Beckman [2 copies], 1-13-75
    - On the Trail of Goodwin Wharton (Talk on Alumni Seminar Day) [2 copies], 5-13-78
    - Arnold Beckman's 80th birthday party (performance by K. Clark and G. Lorden), 4-7-80
    - Caltech As Musical Comedy (for Caltech Women's Club), 1-11-90
    - Arnold Beckman's 92nd birthday party (reprise of material from 80th party by Clark and Lorden), 4-10-92
  - II. Audio Cassettes in the Papers of J. Kent Clark
    - Songs from Take Your Medicine [1.4], 1958
    - Lee and Sympathy (excerpt) [1.9], 1966
    - Selections from Kent Clark Shows [1.16], 1975
    - Let's Advance on Science (song collection) [2.1], 1975
  - III. Phonorecords in Phonorecord Collection
    - The Road to Stockholm [2 copies], ca 1954
    - Who is This Guy DuBridge?, ca 1956
    - Let's Advance on Science (song collection), after 1975
  - IV. Phonorecord in the Papers of J. Kent Clark
    - "Ballad of Chappaquiddick" and "The Richter Scale" [2.3], no date